<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The confession and conuersion of the right honorable, most illustrious, and elect lady, my Lady C. of L.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06121</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16610</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108285</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843946</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843946</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8716</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06121)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8716)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1145:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The confession and conuersion of the right honorable, most illustrious, and elect lady, my Lady C. of L.</title>
                  <author>Linlithgow, Eleanor Livingston, Countess of, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 8-30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wreittoun,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Purports to be by Eleanor Hay Livingston, Countess of Linlithgow, but not in fact by her.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>LinlithgowhEleanor Livingston, --  Countess of.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8716:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8716:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> CONFESSION <hi>AND</hi> CONVERSION <hi>OF THE RIGHT</hi> HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE, MOST ILLVSTRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OVS, <hi>AND ELECT LADY,</hi> MY LADY, C. OF L.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATH. 22.</hi>
               </bibl> Yee erre, not knowing the Scriptures.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. IOHN. 4.</hi>
               </bibl> Dearly beloved, belieue not everie Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, but try the Spirits, whither they be of <hi>GOD,</hi> for many falſe Prophets are gone out into this World.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBVRGH</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Wreittoun.</hi> 1629.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="confession">
            <pb facs="tcp:8716:2"/>
            <head>A CONFESSION.</head>
            <p>AS it was rare, vnexſpected, and long wiſhed for, of all that honored and loved her, ſo is it to be as ſeriouſly to be read, and conſcienciouſlie to bee conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all, or ignorant and wilfull Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts of this land: Not ſo much in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of her rank, perſon, and place, but rather in ſo farre, as that in that faith much beyond her ſexe, ſhe exceeded in knowledge more than many others who yet wilfullie and most ignorantlie still continue in their error.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:8716:2"/>
            <head>PSAL. 77.</head>
            <p>MY voice came to GOD when I cryed; my voice came to GOD &amp; he heard me. In the day of my trouble I ſought the Lord, &amp;c. my ſoule refuſed comfort. I did think vpon GOD, and was troubled. I prayed, and my spirit was full of anguiſh. Thou keept mine eyes waking. I was aſtonied, and could not speake. Pſal. <hi>119.81.</hi> My ſoule fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for thy ſalvation; Yet will I waite for thy word. <hi>82.</hi> Mine eyes faile for thy promiſe, <hi>ſaying,</hi> when wilt thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort me? <hi>92.</hi> Except thy law had beene my delite, I ſhould now haue periſhed in my affliction. I will never forget thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, for by them thou haſt quickned me. I am thine, ſaue me, for I haue ſought thy precepts. <hi>15.</hi> I will meditate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and conſider thy wayes. <hi>59.</hi> I haue conſidered my owne wayes, and turned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> feate to thy testimonies. <hi>67.</hi> Before I was afflicted I went astray, but now I keepe thy Word. <hi>71.</hi> It is good for me that I haue beene afflicted, that I may
<pb facs="tcp:8716:3"/> learne thy ſtatuts. <hi>58.</hi> By thy Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement thou haſt made me wiſer than mine enemies. I haue had more vnderſtanding than all my teachers, for thy teſtimonies are my meditations. I vnderstood more than the ancient, becauſe I delighted in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts. <hi>104.</hi> By thy precepts haue I gotten vnderstanding, therefore I hate all the wayes of falſhood. <hi>29</hi> Now, take from me the way of lying, and grant me gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly thy law. <hi>30.</hi> I haue choſen the way of trueth, and thy iudgement haue I layde before me. <hi>173.</hi> O Lord let thine hand helpe me, for I haue choſen thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts. <hi>176.</hi> I haue gone astray lyke a loſt ſheepe: ſeeke thy ſervant, &amp;c. <hi>103.</hi> The entrance to thy words ſheweth light, and giveth vnderstanding to the ſimple. <hi>124.</hi> Deale with thy ſervant according to thy mercie, and teach me thy ſtatuts. <hi>74.</hi> So they that feare thee, ſeeing me, ſhall rejoyce, becauſe I haue trusted in thy Word.</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8716:3"/>
            <head>THE CON<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERSION AND <hi>CONFESSION OF THE</hi> RIGHT NOBLE C. OF L.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>O ſend out thy light, and thy trueth let them lead mee, let them bring me vnto thine holy hill, and to thy Tabernacles.
<bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 43.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>I will heare what <hi>GOD</hi> the <hi>LORD</hi> will speake, for hee will speake peace vnto his people, and to his Saints; but let them not turne againe vnto follie.
<bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 85.8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Perfitlie knowing, and fullelie aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring my ſoule, that there is no poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilitie of ſalvation to me, but alla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly in the free mercie of GOD, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſatisfaction of his Sonne my only Saviour, who is able to ſaue them to the vttermoſt that come vnto GOD by him, ſeeing he ever liveth to make interc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion for them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25. neither is there ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation in any other, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I renounce and condemne all wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping, or praying to Angels, hee or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8716:4"/> ſhe Saints, not now excepting the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> and conforme to the expreſſe direction of the Angell to Iohn. <hi>Revel.</hi> I take me to worſhip GOD; and as CHRIST, <hi>Math.</hi> 4.10. commandeth him only to ſerue, and to pray to my father. <hi>Math.</hi> 8.9. who is in Heaven, to whom only belongeth religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, both of prayer and praiſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I renounce and condemne all pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in Latin, or any vnknowne tongue to mee, taking mee heereafter, by the grace of GOD to pray with the Spirit, and with vnderſtanding alſo, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. and not to mumble and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my prayers according to the order and diſtinction of beads, which I haue cauſed breake and deſtroy, with preſent and perpetuall thank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>-giving to GOD therefore</p>
            <p n="4">4. I acknowledge with <hi>Ieremie</hi> 10.14. that a molten image is falſhood, they are vanitie and the workes of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors: and therefore caſting away all thoſe abominations of images, pictures, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalles, and pretended reliques: I take
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8716:4"/> me whollie to the pure and plaine Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of IESUS CHRIST, and his holie Sacraments, wherein the lyuelie picture of CHRIST is, and the moſt hallowed Crucifixe that <hi>I</hi> can ſet before mine eyes, handle with mine hands, or carrie vpon my breaſt; wherein I rejoice, and ever ſhall doe, by GODS helpe and aſſiſtance, and finds great comfort in the conference and prayers of GODS Miniſters, who now reſort vnto me frequently: reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by the grace of GOD never there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to craue, nor admit the company and conference of Prieſts, and other teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of lyes, guides of idolatrie; which all now I haue forſaken by the light and force of GODS Spirit: and woes mee that I hearkned ſo long to theſe ſeducers.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I acknowldge that the bowing downe before images is forbidden by GODS Law, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.5. as well as worſhipping of them. That images are altogether bruttiſh and fooliſh. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 10.3. I feare them not, for they can doe no evill, neither is it in them to doe good: but foraſmuch as there is none
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8716:5"/> like to thee O LORD, thou art great, &amp; thy Name is great in might: Who would not feare thee, O KING of Nations? <hi>Ierem.</hi> 10.5.6.7.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I embrace the holy Scriptures of the old and new Teſtament, wherein is the perfite rule of <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>maners,</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that the writs and judgements of all men ſhould be tryed thereby, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced therevnto, or elſe altogether reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. And therefore I will curſe &amp; reject and caſt from me all blaſphemous bookes in write or print, (whereof alace I had ſo many too long) contrare to GODS trueth in theſe holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="7">7. I confeſſe and profeſſe that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are plaine and pure, being <hi>a lampe vnto my feete, and a light vnto my path, Pſal.</hi> 119.105. in all things neceſſare for me to know my ſalvation. And ſeing CHRISS commandeth vs <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.39. to <hi>ſearch the Scriptures,</hi> and the Bereans are commended for ſearching the Scriptures dayly, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11. I condemne the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding of their tranſlations in vulgare languages, and the reading of them by the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8716:5"/> people. And from my heart I deteſt that ſaying, that ignorance is the mother of devotion; bewailing my former ignorance and ſtryving more and more to increſſe in all ſpirituall vnderſtanding.</p>
            <p n="8">8. With <hi>Paul.</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3. I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the commanding to abſteine from meates for conſcience ſake, to be from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing ſpirits, and doctrines of devils, for the Kingdome of GOD is not meate and drink, <hi>but righteouſneſſe, peace, and joy in the holy Ghoſt. Rom.</hi> 14.17. Neither doth that <hi>which entereth in at the mouth defile a man, but that which proceedes out of the mouth that defiles a man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. I acknowledge and belieue, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.24. that I am juſtified freely by GODS grace, through the redemption that is in CHRIST IESUS, without any reſpect to my workes; whereof I neither can, nor ſhould boaſt with the proud Phariſee, but with the penitent Publican. I cry to God continuallie to be mercifull to me, who am a miſerable ſinner, and with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul.</hi> the chiefe of ſinners, and ſo I belieue not the ſatisfaction made by me, but the free
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8716:6"/> remiſſion of ſins, perſwading my ſelfe that <hi>the wages of ſin is death, Rom</hi> 6.23. but the gift of GOD is eternall life, through CHRIST IESUS our LORD, and we his litle floke ſhould not feare, ſeing as our Saviour ſayeth, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32. <hi>It is our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers pleaſure to giue vs a Kingdome,</hi> which we could never merit by our ſelues, or any other creature for vs.</p>
            <p n="10">10. I acknowledge no fire after this life that purgeth vs from our ſins, and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall puniſhments, but as in <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.7. the blood of IESUS CHRIST his Son purgeth vs from all our ſins, without any exception or deſtruction of ſin what-ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, and as the ſoules of the wicked im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly after death goe to hell, ſo the ſoules of the godly goe to Heaven.</p>
            <p n="11">11. I acknowledge and belieue with S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16. that the Cup in the Lords Supper is not the blood, but fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiuely the communion of his bodie. And with <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.30. The way how to eate and drink of this body is to belieue in him, and the Doctors, and Cannons of the Roman Church affirmeth the ſame
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8716:6"/> with vs, for the holy Scripture is full of ſuch maner of ſpeaches; and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour himſelfe in this ſame place ſayeth that <hi>whoſoever beleiveth in him ſhall not thirſt,</hi> plainely making vs to vnderſtand that this thirſt is quenched only by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiving, and not by the drinking at the mouth: and in <hi>Ioh.</hi> 6.56. he ſayeth, <hi>Whoſoever eateth my fleſh, and drinketh my blood, abideth in me and I in him:</hi> and in verſe 35. <hi>Who comes vnto mee ſhall not hunger,</hi> and <hi>who beleiveth in mee ſhall never thirst:</hi> So he eateth and drinketh, who commeth vnto me, who beleiveth in me, and abideth in mee. and alitle after, having ſaid, <hi>Who belei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in me hath eternall life,</hi> inferreth thereby that he is the bread of lyfe. Hee is then meate indeed, but for our ſoules, not for our bodyes; which is to be had by beleiving, not by ſwallowing. And ſo expondeth <hi>Origen</hi> an ancient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in his Hom. 12. in <hi>Math.</hi> this ſame place. According to the Apoſtle his exhortation, I am heartly deſirous after tryall of my ſelfe, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8716:7"/> oft to eate of that bread, and drink of that Cup, and ſo (as praiſed be GOD) I latelie did rrceaue that holie Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, publicklie in GODS Sanctuarie, vnder both the kynds, for the food of my ſoule, whereby now I find great peace and comfort.</p>
            <p n="12">12. I acknowledge alſo, and beleiue, that the Maſſe is not a propitiatorie ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, but a blaſphemous, and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous abomination, altogether deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie to CHRISTS propitiatorie ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, who once in the end of the world to appeare, came to put away ſinne, by that only one ſacrifice of himſelfe, and who once was offered to beare the ſinnes of many, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.26.28. and by that one offering, for ever hee hath perfited all them that are ſanctified, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. <hi>v.</hi> 14.15.</p>
            <p n="13">13. I acknowledge, and beleiue, that the Pope is not CHRISTS Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>care, nor Peters ſucceſſour, but hee is that man of ſinne, the ſonne of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e great Antichriſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. Who
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8716:7"/> will judge all men, whether they bee Kings or ſubjects, and bee judged of none, and will haue all men vnder paine of damnation to bee ſubject to him, as their owne ſupreame Lord, both in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and temporall things.</p>
            <p>I did alſo before my converſion after long tryall find ſome great oddes, and verie remarkable differences betweene the Paſtors of the reformed Kirk, and that of the Roman Kirk: And firſt that the Paſtors of the reformed Kirk would bee judged by the word of GOD; but the Paſtors of the Roman Kirk would be judges of the word of GOD.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The reformed Paſtors would bee ruled; but the Roman Kirk would bee the rule themſelues, ſaying, that the Kirk is ſoveraigne judge of all doubts of faith, and that it can not erre. And ſo I perceaue in this queſtion: If the Roman Kirk may erre; or if it bee ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne and infallible judge, it muſt bee that the Roman Kirk ſhall be judge, and ſo conſequentlie ſhee ſhall be both judge and partie.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:8716:8"/>
            <p>I haue alſo obſerved this difference betweene the two religions, which is, that the reformed Kirk hath no rules that teacheth vices: but the Roman Kirk hath ſundrie rules that teacheth men to doe evill, and to diſobey GOD. Such is the rule of the councell of <hi>Constance,</hi> that a man is not bound to keepe any faith and truth to Hereticks. Such is the doctrine, that the Pope may diſpenſe with the expreſſe Commandeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of GOD, by diſpenſing with the Cup in the Sacrament, by diſpenſing with othes and vowes, in granting permiſſion to a man to man-ſweare himſelfe, neither yet to performe any wayes that which wee haue promiſed to GOD. Such are the diſobedience of young infants to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their fathers and mothers, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained &amp; authorized by the Roman Kirk, when a young childe is entred into a cloſter contrare the will of his father.</p>
            <p>Such are alſo the foundations of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Bordels, whereby the Pope him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe draweth great tribute.</p>
            <p>Such are alſo the revolt of ſubjects
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8716:8"/> from their Prince, and againſt them, when it ſhall pleaſe the people to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe with their Oath of alledgeance, which they haue ſworne to their King.</p>
            <p>I haue found alſo the plaine text of Scripture in many places moſt pittiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly corrupted, and wrongouſly perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Roman Kirk, and ſome I remarked moſt carefully, as followeth.</p>
            <p>It is ſaid in the 2 Epiſt. to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> verſe 21. <hi>That Iakob worſhipped GOD leaning vpon the end of his ſtaffe;</hi> but the Byble of the Roman Kirk hath, <hi>Iakob worſhipped the end of his staffe,</hi> thereby to eſtabliſh the adoration of Creatures.</p>
            <p>The lyke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orruption is in the Pſal. 99. <hi>v.</hi> 5. Where David ſayeth <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe towards his footſtoole:</hi> the Roman Bible hath, <hi>Worſhippe his footſtoole:</hi> and in Geneſ. 3. <hi>v.</hi> 15. GOD ſaid, <hi>The ſeede of the woman ſhould treade downe the head of the Serpent:</hi> the Roman Kirk hath, <hi>the woman ſhall bruiſe the head of the Serpent;</hi> that is the Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſhall bruiſe downe the head, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:8716:9"/>
            <p>Againe in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Pauls Epiſt. Rom. 11 6. is cutted off, two lynes being omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: For theſe are the words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>But if it bee of workes it is no more of grace, or elſe were workes no more workes,</hi> which are left out in the vulgare tranſlation.</p>
            <p>And where S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Peter ſayeth, <hi>Heere are two ſwords:</hi> the Roman Kirk moſt ridicoulouſlie expondeth thus, that the Pope hath power over the ſpirituall and temporall.</p>
            <p>And where the Evangeliſt ſayeth, <hi>Doe this in rememberance of mee:</hi> the Romiſh Church expoundeth thus, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice my body in a ſacrifice propiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atorie for the quick and the dead.</p>
            <p>And another falſhood I remember, is, where our Saviour ſpeaking of the Cuppe in the Sacrament, ſayeth, <hi>This Cuppe is the new Covenant in my blood which is ſhed for you:</hi> But the Bible of the Romiſh Church hath into it, <hi>This Cuppe is the new Covenant in my blood, which ſhall bee ſhed for you,</hi> leaſt a man ſhould perceaue that IESVS
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8716:9"/> CHRIST ſpake of a ſacramentall ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his bloode: For as yet hee had not then really ſhed his bloode which hee had begunne to ſhed in his paſſion.</p>
            <p>Theſe and many other falſhoods did I many tymes remarke, as they were objected vnto me, yet did I ever miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regard them, being ever diſcontented that any ſhould ſpeake to mee of ſuch hereticall opinions, (as I called them) becauſe my ghoſtly fathers aſſured mee continually that it was a deadly ſinne any wayes to doubt, or to let it ſo much as once enter into my thought, that ever the Church might or could erre, continually dinging in my eares a warrant out of the Prophet <hi>Malachie;</hi> cap. 2, verſe 8. that the Preiſts cannot erre, where it is thus read, <hi>The Preists lips ſhall keepe knowledge, and they ſhall ſeeke the law at his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This many yeeres contented mee, till at laſt in my old dayes GOD ſo happily moved my heart to heare the trueth of better and ſounder inſtructers,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8716:10"/> and their warrand, (I praiſe GOD for it) who ſheweth to me that the words of the Prophet are, and ought to bee tranſlated thus, yet men that are ledde with an opinion that the Kirk can not erre will never conſider this: <hi>The Preiſts lippes ſhould keepe knowledge:</hi> For they that tranſlate thus the words, and <hi>that they ſhall ſeeke the law at his mouth,</hi> they did never intend to ſhew thereby, that GOD did make heere a promiſe that ſo it ſhall bee for ever, but onely to ſhew that this it the law and commaadement of GOD, teaching what the Preiſts and people ſhould doe, and ought to doe, even as in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, <hi>Thou ſhall haue no other GODS but mee:</hi> Now I find that the words doe not promiſe that the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites ſhould alwayes acknowledge and worſhippe IEHOVA the true GOD a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, (for as may bee ſeene in the text within fourtie dayes the event ſhewed the contrarie) but ſhew what they ought to doe, but the wordes are a Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement recited, not a promiſe made:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8716:10"/> For the words of the fourth verſe did ſhow it: Therefore men not partially led may eaſily perceaue that the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of the reformed Kirk is moſt perfect of all, ſhowing not onely the ſenſe and meaning of the law, but alſo how it did bind the people and Prieſt, and how they ought to obey it.</p>
            <p>By this I thinke it no hereſie, and I beleiue with the reformed Kirk that it is GODS holy trueth, that Preiſts ſucceeding in the place and office of <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> may erre, and haue erred: yea, <hi>I</hi> thinke it the greateſt er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of all errors to thinke that a man can not erre, were hee never ſo holie. <hi>I</hi> perceaue now <hi>Moſes</hi> Chayre in the which the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> did ſit, was the ſeate wherein they were wont to read the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the expoſitions thereof to the people, for what they there did teach was true, and therefore CHRIST commanded them to obey it. To ſitte in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chaire, I vnderſtand, is to teach <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> doctrine, but (as the Iewes made
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8716:11"/> GODS law voyd by their owne gloſſes &amp; traditions) they erred moſt damnablie, and were no more in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chaire, and ſo the people were no more bound to obey it. For at that tyme CHRIST himſelfe called their doctrine ſowre lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and warned his Diſciples to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of it.</p>
            <p>I know alſo, and fimelie now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, that it was never the purpoſe of GODS Spirit in that place, or by theſe wordes to teach, that the Law ſhould alwayes bee taught truelie and infalla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie by the Prieſts and Paſtors, who ſucceede <hi>Moſes</hi> or the Apoſtles in the Church by a continued ſucceſſion: For that is a falſhoode contrare to experience in all ages: That this is moſt certaine, <hi>I</hi> deſire but any of a contrare opinion to read but the ſame verie place with an indifferent and vnprejudged minde, which confutes it moſt evidently: For in reading the ſame attentiuelie, <hi>I</hi> find the Prieſts vnto whom the Prophet there ſpeaketh in theſe places, were Levits, and directly ſucceded <hi>Aaron</hi> in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8716:11"/> the Preiſthood: And yet yee ſee by the plaine text they were departed out of the way: they cauſed many fall in the law by their corrupt gloſſe, and their abuſe of the Covenant of <hi>Levi,</hi> as it appeareth moſt clearely into the next words following immediatly: Yea, ſome of them (yee ſee) had ſacrificed to Idolles, which I haue read my ſelfe in <hi>Ioſephus</hi> hiſtorie of theſe tymes, and therefore the LORD threatneth to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt their ſeede by cutting off the male progenie, and to caſt the dung of their ſacrifices in their faces.</p>
            <p>Finally I hope now in the mercie of GOD yet before I die, to heare a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth ſermons in GODS true Kirk: for now my onely joy is my new birth, that by the mercie of my GOD I am regenerate, and of a daughter of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and death, that haue beene from my naturall birth, am now made a daughter of light and lyfe in my old age, and my ſetled peace and comfort is my ſpirituall marriage with my head
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8716:12"/> and husband the LORD IESUS CHRIST, who hath marryed mee to himſelfe in trueth and everlaſting compaſſion, and will take from mee my old corrupt garment, and clothe mee with the white robe of his righteouſneſſe, ſo that my nakedneſſe ſhall never appeare any more.</p>
            <p>Now O LORD my GOD, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Father in thy CHRIST, my ſweete SAVIOUR, let thy Spirit quicken mee more and more, thy wiſdome guide mee, thy grace ſanctifie mee, and thy Word inſtruct me: Let the holy Ghoſt of whom thy Sonne my SAVIOUR was conceived, beget in mee, and mee in thee, by the immortall ſeede of thy Word: Let my faith conceaue, my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance honour thee, my loue em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace thee, my zeale continuallie keepe thee with mee, till the comming againe of thy Sonne for my ever hoped glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification: So come vnto mee LORD IESUS, come quicklie, Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bleſſed be the</hi> LORD, <hi>for he hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me his mercifull kindneſſe. Pſal</hi> 31.21.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8716:12"/> 
               <hi>Why art thou cast downe my ſoule, and why art thou diſquyeted within mee? hope in GOD, for I ſhall yet praiſe him, who is the hope of my Salvation, and my</hi> GOD. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.11.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSALME. XLI.I.</bibl> 
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Waited patiently vpon the LORD, and hee inclyned vnto mee, and heard my cry. Hee brought mee alſo out of the horrible pit, out of the myrie clay, and ſet my feete vpon the Rocke, and ordered my goings. And hee hath put into my mouth a new ſong of Praiſe vnto our God. Many ſhall ſee it, and feare, and ſhall truſt into the LORD. Bleſſed is the man that maketh the LORD his truſt, and regardeth not the proud, nor ſuch as turne aſyde to lyes.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7.</hi> Then ſaid I, loe, I come, for in the roll of thy booke it is written of mee, I deſire to doe thy good will, O my GOD. Yea, thy law is within my heart, I haue declared thy righteouſneſſe in the great
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8716:13"/> congregation: Loe, I will not refraine my lips, O LORD, thou knoweſt.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSALME 86.11.</bibl> 
               <p>Teach mee thy way, O LORD, and I will walke in thy trueth, knit my heart vnto thee, that I may feare thy Name.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <hi>17.</hi> Shew a token of thy goodneſſe toward mee, that they which hate mee, may ſee it, and bee aſhamed, becauſe thou LORD hath helped me, and conforted me.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSALME 116.6.</bibl> The LORD preſerveth the ſimple, I was in miſerie, and hee ſaved mee. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vnto thy rest, O my ſoule, for the LORD hath beene beneficiall vnto thee.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSALME 109.26.</bibl> Helpe mee O LORD my GOD, ſaue mee according to thy mercie, and they ſhall know that this is thy hand, and that thou LORD hast done it. If the LORD had not helped mee, my ſoule had almoſt dwelt in ſilence.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSALME 101.</bibl> Mine eyes ſhall bee vnto the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the Land, that they may dwell with mee: Hee that walketh in a perfite
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8716:13"/> way ſhall ſerue mee, there ſhall no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceatfull perſon dwell in mine houſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall hee that telleth lyes remaine in my ſight.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSALME. 56.12.</bibl> I will now render praiſe vnto thee, <hi>13</hi> For thou haſt delyvered my ſoule from death, and my feete frm falling, that I may walke before GOD in the light of the living.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSALME 103.</bibl> Bleſſed bee the Name of the LORD from hencefoorth and for ever,</q>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A PRAYER.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 45.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <hi>10</hi> Hearken (O daughter) and conſider, encline thine eare, forget alſo thine owne people, and fathers houſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AS thou O LORD art great and wonderfull in all thy workes: yet thy mercie ſhineth aboue all thinges:
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8716:14"/> Albeit I forſooke thee O LORD, yet thou haſt not forſaken mee: I haue turned my back to thee, yet thou calleſt mee thy Childe: All that thou requireſt at mine hands is, that I would hearken vnto thee. And why ſhould I not hearken vnto thee, ſith that all our deſtruction came from thence, that our fathers turned their eares from thee, to liſten vnto the voice of the ſlie and ſubtile Serpent? Grant me grace that I may haue a willing and obedient heart, that by the meanes of good foode, that I ſhall receaue in thy Word, which alace too long I haue forſaken, I may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get my wicked nature, originall ſin, and all the vices which I did bring with mee from my mothers wombe; that I forget the world, to giue my ſelfe wholly vnto thee, and thy ſervice; that <hi>I</hi> forget mine owne workes, and mine owne opinions, to depend wholly on thy grace. And if the Bride, and new married woman forſake, and leaue her fathers houſe to follow her husband: if ſhe leaue the ſport and paſtime of her youth, to goe about her houſwifrie, and to conforme her ſelfe vnto her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8716:14"/> why ſhould not I alas! forſake that which diſpleaſeth thee, to be agreeable vnto thy Son IESUS CHRIST, which in ſo great mercie hath wedded me? And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I was a ſtraunger from his league, &amp; promiſes of everlaſting lyfe, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding he hath joyned himſelfe vnto me in hearty loue, &amp; ratified his league with his precious blood. Let me therefore O Lord be as his chaſt and faithfull ſpouſe, and let me be obedient vnto the will of our good LORD, which doth me this honour to place me by his ſide, and to take mee not only for his <hi>ſervant,</hi> but alſo for his <hi>child,</hi> his <hi>friend, his deare and welbeloved Spouſe, Ioh.</hi> 15. Grant me O LORD that I follow no more ſtrange Gods to delight in them, but that my loue and affection be wholly ſet on him. I will therefore endevour my ſelfe to pleaſe him. I will loue him, and loue that which he loveth. I will honour him, ſith he hath ſo much honoured mee. I will forſake all things to follow him, ſee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing he forſooke the Heavens to ſaue mee on earth. O happie marriage! Of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage of Adam and Eue came ſo many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifts,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8716:15"/> ſo many wretches, and miſerable catiues, bond-ſlaues to Sathan, and of their owne nature, deteſtable and abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable before the face of GOD. But of this holy marriage, are new borne, the elect, the veſſels of glorie, the children of GOD, the heires of everlaſting lyfe: whom GOD ſo loveth and eſteemeth, taking pleaſure in their beautie, wherewith he doth adorne and deck them through his Son CHRIST IESUS: which gifts LORD make me partaker thereof, and let the praiſe be aſcribed vnto thee, for that great and glorious light of thy Word, ſhowne vnto me, from henceforth and for ever,</p>
            <closer>AMEN.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="concluding_note">
            <p>THis profeſſion of faith, meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, prayers, and prayſes, as they were moſt joyfullie; and conſtantlie vttered, and declared before many ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable men and women: So were they moſt heartilie ſealed and ſubſcryved by the right religious, moſt noble, and truely wiſe La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, <date>the 25. of Maij.</date>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8716:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
